Let's start this section by learning
how the DOM really works behind the scenes
and more specifically how the DOM is organized internally.
This will make it easier to understand everything else
that's gonna follow in this section.
So first, remember that the DOM
is basically the interface between all JavaScript code
and the browser, or more specifically HTML documents
that are rendered in and by the browser.
Now we have written a ton of JavaScript code
in this course so far,
but many times completely without interacting
with the browser so without using the DOM.
Right?
But now we're back to working with webpages
and therefore with the DOM
and this time we're going to learn as much as possible
about the DOM and how to create amazing dynamic effects.
So let's remember what we already know about the DOM,
which is that we can use it to make
JavaScript interact with the browser
and again more specifically we can create
and modify and delete elements,
set styles and classes and attributes
and listen and respond to events.
In practice this works because a DOM tree
is generated from any HTML document
and a DOM tree is a tree like structure made out of nodes
which looks something like this.
And we can then interact with this tree
as we already did a couple of times in this course.
Now how does that interaction actually work?
Well the DOM is a very complex API
which remember stands for application programming interface.
So it's the interface we can use to
programmatically interact with the DOM.
In practice that means that the DOM
contains a ton of methods and properties
that we use to interact with the DOM tree
such as the querySelector, addEventListener
or createElement methods,
or also the innerHTML, textContent or children properties
and many, many more.
Now in the DOM there are different types of nodes
just as I mentioned before.
For example some nodes are HTML elements
but others are just text, remember?
And this is really important to understand
because all these DOM methods and properties
are organized into these different types of objects.
And so let's now take a look at how the DOM API
is organized behind the scenes.
So first, every single note in the DOM tree
is of the type, node.
And such as everything else in JavaScript,
each node is represented in JavaScript by an object.
This object gets access to special node methods
and properties, such as text content, child nodes,
parent nodes, clone nodes and many others.
Now we already know that there are different types of nodes.
Right?
So how should these be represented?
Well, this node type has a couple of child types so to say.
And these are the element type, the text type,
the comment type and also the document type.
So whenever there is text inside any element,
we already know that it gets its own node.
Right?
And that node will be of the type, text.
And the same actually happens for HTML comments
and that's because the rule is that everything
that's in the HTML has to go into the DOM as well.
Now for the element itself there is
the element type of node.
And this type of node gives each HTML access
to a ton of useful properties
such as innerHTML, classList, children or parent element.
There are also many useful methods
like append, remove, insertAdjacentHTML, querySelector,
closest and that's just to name a few.
So again, each element will be represented internally
as an object.
Now just to make this complete,
the element type has internally an HTML element,
child type.
And that element type itself has exactly one child type
for each HTML element that exists in HTML.
So we have a special type for buttons,
a special type for images,
for links, and so on and so forth.
And that's important because each of these HTML elements
can have different unique properties.
For example and image has a source attribute in HTML
which no other element has.
Or the anchor element for links
has the HREF attribute which also no other element has.
And so the DOM needs a way of storing
these different attributes
and therefore different types
of HTML elements were created in the DOM API.
And just to make sure that we're all on the same page here,
this diagram that I'm showing you here
is of course not a DOM tree.
Right?
So this is not a representation of any HTML document.
This is just a way that different types of nodes
are represented behind the scenes in the DOM API.
Now, right?
But anyway, now comes the really important part,
because what makes all of this work
is something called inheritance.
So what is inheritance?
Well inheritance means that all the child types
will also get access to the methods and properties
of all their parent node types.
For example an HTML element will get access to everything
from the element type, like innerHTML, or classList
or all these other methods and properties.
And besides that it will also get access to everything
from the node type because that is also its parent type.
Okay?
So we can think of this as though
the HTML button element for example,
is also an element and also a node.
All right?
Now this might seem all a bit weird and confusing
but don't worry.
We will learn why this kind of inheritance works very soon
when we finally talk about object oriented JavaScript.
For now, what I want you to understand is that a DOM API
is broken up into these different types of nodes.
I also want you to understand that each
of these types of nodes
has access to different properties and methods
and that some of them
even inherit more properties and methods
from their ancestors in this organization.
All right?
Now we didn't talk yet about the documents node type.
So document, which we use all the time in DOM manipulation
is in fact just another type of node
so it contains important methods,
such as querySelector, createElement
and getElement by I.D.
And note how querySelector
is available on both the document and element types.
So keep this in mind because it will be important later on.
All right, and now there is just
one final missing piece here
because the DOM API actually needs a way
of allowing all the node types to listen to events.
And remember we usually listen for events by calling the
addEventListener method on an element or the document.
Right?
So why does that actually work?
Well its because there is a special node type called
EventTarget which is a parent of both the node type
and also the window node type.
And so with this, thanks to inheritance,
we can call addEventListener on every single type of node
in the DOM API because all elements
as well as document and window,
and even text and comment will inherit this method
and therefore we will be able to use addEventListener
on all of them just as if it was their own method.
Now just to be clear, we do never
manually create an eventTarget object.
Okay.
This is just an abstract type
that we do not use in practice.
This all really happens behind the scenes
to make all the functionality work as we expect it to work.
So in a nutshell this is how the DOM API works
and is structured behind the scenes.
There are still some simplifications here
but this is all that really matters.
And I really wish that I could have had this diagram
when I learnt JavaScript for the first time.
Because I really think this helps structuring
all this information in your mind.
Now if you want to go even deeper than this
there is still tons of material
that you can check out in the MDN documentation
and if you ask me it's all really fascinating.
But again, all that you need to know
is really in this lecture.
It took me a lot of hours to put this one together
but I think it was well worth it
and I hope you think the same.
But anyway lets now move on
to the practical part Of this section
were we will then
finally use many of these things in action.